Guide to the Samuel J. Tilden papers, 1794-1886 [bulk 1835-1876]
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
- Series X. Writings and Speeches, ca. 1820s - 1886, n.d; 39900; 9 boxes, 3.75 linear feet.
  - X. B. Speeches, 1831 - 1880, n.d.; 39954
    Tilden had been a well-known orator since his youth, and his speeches illustrate the development of his ideology across the span of his career. A speech made at an 1831 Democratic Republican Party meeting suggests that even at the age of 17, Tilden had already developed a significant degree of political acumen. He continued to speak at meetings of the Democratic Republicans, Whigs, and Free-Soilers through the 1840s, and became a regular speaker for the Democratic Party on both local and national platforms in the 1860s and 1870s. Common themes included banking and currency; the Civil War; taxation; and political reform. Multiple drafts of his 1875 inaugural speech and his annual messages to the legislation in Albany can be found here, as can his concession speech after the contested presidential election of 1876. One file of interviews with Tilden given between 1872 and 1880, and an index to his published speeches are filed at the beginning of this series. Speeches are arranged chronologically.
    - Interviews, 1872 - 1880, n.d.; 39955 (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - Index of published speeches, 1868 - 1876; 39956 (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - Sketch for speech at political meeting, 1831; 39957 (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Address at the Hudson Convention, 1833; 39958 (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - Speech to the Democratic Republican Young Men of the County of Columbia, 1834; 39959 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Whig meeting at New Lebanon, 1834; 39960 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - The Divorce of Bank and State, 1838; 39961 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Address to Anti-Masonic electors of Columbia County, ca. 1830s; 39962 (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - Speech at New Lebanon on currency, taxes and wages, 1840; 39963; Includes reprint. (Box 76, Folder 9-10)
    - Address for Nominating Committee of 1844, 39964 (Box 76, Folder 11)
    - Speech at the Convention of 1846, 39965 (Box 76, Folder 12)
    - Remarks on the Single District System, 1848; 39966 (Box 76, Folder 13)
    - Convention address regarding Civil War, 1861; 39967 (Box 76, Folder 14)
    - Speech to merchants and bankers meeting, 1864; 39968 (Box 76, Folder 15)
    - To a Delegate to the Democratic Presidential Convention at Chicago, 1864; 39969 (Box 76, Folder 16)
    - Remarks on the death of Dean Richmond, 1866; 39970 (Box 76, Folder 17)
    - Restoring Representation in Congress to the Southern States, 1866; 39971 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Speech at the Constitutional Convention, 1867; 39972; Reprint (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Union Square speech, 1866; 39973; Includes reprint (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified drafts, 1867; 39974 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Speech at the Democratic State Convention, 1868; 39975; Reprint (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - With Whom Shall We Self-Govern?, 1868; 39976 (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - Untitled speech, 1868; 39977 (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - Taxation in the United States, 1868; 39978; Reprint (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - Speech at Milwaukee, 1868; 39979 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - Albany speech opposing charter revision, 1870; 39980 (Box 77, Folder 10)
    - Address to judicial convention, 1870; 39981 (Box 77, Folder 11)
    - Speech at the Democratic State Convention, 1871; 39982; Reprint (Box 77, Folder 12)
    - Cooper Union address, 1871; 39983 (Box 77, Folder 13)
    - Assembly speech on judicial reform, 1872; 39984 (Box 77, Folder 14)
    - Remarks before Ohio Bar Association, 1872; 39985 (Box 77, Folder 15)
    - Assembly speech on new charter, 1872; 39986 (Box 77, Folder 16)
    - Convention speech, 1874; 39987 (Box 77, Folder 17)
    - Speech at the Manhattan Club, 1874; 39988; Includes reprint (Box 77, Folder 18)
    - Reception of the Young Men's Democratic Club, 1874; 39989; Reprint (Box 77, Folder 19)
    - Inauguration speech, 1875; 39990; Reprint (Box 77, Folder 20)
    - First Annual Address to the Legislature, 1875 Jan; 39991 (Box 77, Folder 21-22)
    - First Annual Address to the Legislature, 1875 Jan; 39992 (Box 78, Folder 1-2)
    - Special Message to Legislature, 1875 May; 39993 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Speech to Buffalo Board of Trade, 1875; 39994; Includes reprint (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Address at the Central New York Fair, 1875; 39995; Reprint (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Speeches at Ft. Edward, 1875; 39996 (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - Remarks at the Hebrew Charity Fair, 1875; 39997; Reprint (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - Address on reduction of state taxes, 1875; 39998 (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - Second Annual Address to the Legislature, 1876 Jan; 39999 (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - Address before Conference of Charities, 1876; 40000 (Box 78, Folder 10)
    - Address to the farmers of Columbia County, 1875; 40001; Reprint (Box 78, Folder 11)
    - Concession speech, 1876; 40002 (Box 78, Folder 12)
    - Speech to Governor Robinson, 1877; 40003; Includes reprint (Box 78, Folder 13)
    - Speech at the Manhattan Club, 1877; 40004 (Box 78, Folder 14)
    - Dinner speech for Junius Spencer Morgan, 1877; 40005 (Box 78, Folder 15)
    - Speech to the delegates from the State of New York to the Democratic National Convention, 1880; 40006; Reprint (Box 78, Folder 16)
    - Speech at Tarrytown, 1880; 40007; Includes reprint (Box 78, Folder 17)
    - Remarks at the Iroqouis Club, 1884; 40008; Reprint (Box 78, Folder 18)
    - Acceptance speech, n.d.; 40009 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Sketch of a speech on the Tariff at the Tabernacle, n.d.; 40010 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Speech relating to Canal Commission, n.d.; 40011 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified fragments, 1834 - 1876, n.d.; 40012 (Box 79, Folder 4-5)
- Series XI. Personal papers, 1785 - 1929; 40013; 21 boxes, 6 volumes; 9.4 linear feet
  This series contains material relating to Tilden's personal financial and legal activities; his investments in real estate and railroad companies; family papers and genealogical research; and a collection of personal miscellany such as school work, ephemera, and photographs.
  - XI. A. Financial and legal, 1785 - 1919; 40014
    This series contains material related to Tilden's personal finances. Items include documents relating to his estate; powers of attorney and other legal instruments; promissory notes; and case files relating to an income tax suit. Most of Tilden's personal fortune was made through investments in mines, railroads, and real estate. His considerable holdings in Brooklyn, Long Island, Albany, New Lebanon and elsewhere are documented by deeds, indentures, and maps. His activities as a stockholder in numerous railroad companies, including the New York Elevated, Terre Haute, Altamont & St. Louis, and the Pittsburg, Ft. Wayne & Detroit railways are contained in multiple files.
    - General files, 40015
      - Bank protests, 1851 - 1881; 40016 (Box 79, Folder 6)
      - Cancelled checks, 1844 - 1857; 40017 (Box 79, Folder 7)
      - Estate, 1879 - 1919, n.d.; 40018 (Box 79, Folder 8)
      - Powers of Attorney, 1857, 1877, 1881; 40019 (Box 79, Folder 9)
      - Promisory notes, 1844 - 1885; 40020 (Box 79, Folder 10)
      - Receipts, 1807, 1834 - 1886; 40021 (Box 79, Folder 11)
      - Stock certificates, 1855 - 1868; 40022 (Box 79, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous legal documents, 1844 - 1882, n.d.; 40023 (Box 79, Folder 13)
    - Income tax suit, 40024
      - Correspondence, 1863 - 1882, n.d.; 40025 (Box 80, Folder 1-2)
      - Case files, 1879 - 1882, n.d.; 40026 (Box 80, Folder 3-5)
    - Coal and Railroad investments, 40027
      - Data on coal mines, 1848 - 1850; 40029 (Box 80, Folder 7)
      - Callaway Mining Company, 1861 - 1878; 40028 (Box 80, Folder 6)
      - Bennington and Rutland RR, 1869 - 1870; 40030 (Box 80, Folder 8)
      - Chicago & Alton RR, 1862 - 1864; 40031 (Box 80, Folder 9)
      - Chicago & Northwestern RR, 1864 - 1865; 40032 (Box 81, Folder 1)
      - McGregor Western RR, 1863 - 1864; 40033 (Box 81, Folder 2)
      - Metropolitan Railway, 1875; 40034 (Box 81, Folder 3)
      - Mexican National Railway, 1863 - 1864; 40035 (Box 81, Folder 4)
      - New York Elevated Railway, 1879 - 1880; 40036 (Box 81, Folder 5-6)
      - Pittsburg, Ft. Wayne & Chicago RR, 1862 - 1883; 40037 (Box 81, Folder 7-8)
      - Terre Haute, Alton & St. Louis RR, 1862; 40038 (Box 82, Folder 1-3)
      - Union Pacific RR, 1853, 1882; 40039 (Box 82, Folder 4)
      - Other railroads, 1859 - 1885; 40040 (Box 82, Folder 5-6)
      - Railroad maps and surveys, 1859 - 1879, n.d.; 40041; Oversized. (Box 93)
    - Real estate, 40042
      - Fifth Avenue, New York City, 1850 - 1873; 40043 (Box 82, Folder 7)
      - Albany, New York, 1874; 40044 (Box 82, Folder 8)
      - Brooklyn, New York, 1849 - 1898; 40045 (Box 82, Folder 9)
      - Brooklyn, New York, 1849 - 1898; 40046 (Box 83, Folder 1-3)
      - Brooklyn, New York, 1849 - 1898; 40047; Oversized. (Box 91, Folder 1-5)
      - Cayuga county, New York, 1846; 40048 (Box 83, Folder 4)
      - Englewood, New Jersey, 1869 - 1888; 40049 (Box 83, Folder 5-6)
      - Grammercy Place, New York City, 1859 - 1889; 40050 (Box 83, Folder 7-8)
      - Islip, New York, 1871; 40051 (Box 83, Folder 9)
      - Michigan, 1866 - 1886, n.d.; 40052 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Malone, New York, 1872; 40053 (Box 84, Folder 2)
      - New Lebanon, New York, 1785, 1879, 1885; 40054 (Box 84, Folder 3)
      - Pennsylvania, 1857 - 1877; 40055 (Box 84, Folder 4)
      - Vermont, 1868; 40056 (Box 84, Folder 5)
      - Unidentified properties, 1850 - 1886; 40057 (Box 84, Folder 6)
      - Unidentified properties, 1850 - 1886; 40058
      - Miscellaneous deeds and indentures, 1818 - 1881; 40059 (Box 84, Folder 7-8)
  - XI. B. Personal miscellany, 1830 - 1886; 40060
    The personal miscellany series contains an inventory of personal items including awards; catalogs and indices to his extensive personal library; material relating to the management of his Greystone estate in Yonkers; and photographs. Certificates held in the collection include his admission to the New York State Bar Association and his passport. A house book and wine inventory are among the items pertaining to his home at Greystone. Photographs include family members (Laura Pelton and Caroline Tilden in particular), but mainly represent Tilden's friends in his social and political spheres, such as William H. Wickham, Charles A. Dana, and Leila Morse Rummel, daughter of Samuel Morse. Many are of Tilden himself at various stages of his adult life. School notes dating from his early years are few, but some notes dating from his college and law school years have been preserved. One file of minutes from the New Lebanon Debate Society demonstrates Tilden's precocious political acuity.
    - Address and appointment books, 1843 - 1844, n.d.; 40061 (Box 84, Folder 9-10)
    - Awards and certificates, 1844 - 1883; 40062 (Box 84, Folder 11)
    - Awards and Certificates, 1845 - 1875; 40063; Oversized material, rolled. (Box 91)
    - Awards and certificates, 1876, nd; 40064; Oversized material. (Box 92, Folder 6)
    - Awards and certificates, 1876, nd; 40065; Oversized material.
    - Business cards and trade cards, 40066 (Box 84, Folder 12)
    - Catalogs, 40067
      - Manuscript Catalog of His Library, ca. 1883; 40068 (Volume 8)
      - Library catalog, n.d; 40069 (Volume 9)
      - Catalogue of Law Books in His Office {1877, 40070 (Volume 10)
      - Shelf inventory of books, pamphlets, periodicals and prints, 1887; 40071 (Volume 11)
    - Greystone, 40072
      - Wine inventory and temperature records, 1879; 40073 (Box 84, Folder 13)
      - Architectural drawings and designs, undated; 40074; Currently closed for preservation treatement. (Box 94-98)
      - Architectural drawings and designs, undated; 40075
      - House book, 40076 (Volume 12)
    - Library lending notes, 40077 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of the New Lebanon Debate Society, 1830; 40078 (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - Notebooks, n.d.; 40079 (Box 85, Folder 3)
    - Pets and livestock, 40080
      - Breeder's register, 1883 - 1886; 40081 (Volume 13)
      - Miscellaneous material, 40082 (Box 85, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, 40083
      - Cooper, Edward, n.d.; 40084 (Box 85, Folder 5)
      - Cooper, Peter, n.d; 40085 (Box 85, Folder 6)
      - Dana, Charles, n.d.; 40086 (Box 85, Folder 7)
      - Douglas, Stephen, n.d.; 40087 (Box 85, Folder 8)
      - Pelton, Laura A., n.d.; 40088 (Box 85, Folder 9)
      - Rummel, Leila Morse, 1874 - 1881; 40089 (Box 85, Folder 10)
      - Stauffe, Marie Celeste, n.d.; 40090 (Box 85, Folder 11)
      - Steedman, Samuel J. Tilden, ca. 1881; 40091 (Box 85, Folder 12)
      - Tilden, Caroline M., 1882; 40092 (Box 85, Folder 13)
      - Tilden, Samuel J., 1876 - 1885, n.d.; 40093; Folder 15 contains a glass negative. (Box 85, Folder 14-15)
      - Wickham, William H., n.d.; 40094 (Box 85, Folder 16)
      - Unidentified, n.d.; 40095 (Box 85, Folder 17)
      - Pets and livestock, 1877 - 1884, n.d.; 40096 (Box 85, Folder 18)
      - Tilden memorial monument, n.d.; 40097 (Box 86, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, n.d.; 40098 (Box 86, Folder 2)
    - School notes and notebooks, 40099 (Box 86, Folder 3-5)
    - Scrapbook, 1877; 40100 (Box 86, Folder 6)
    - Tickets and ephemera, 1831 - 1844, 1874, n.d; 40101 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1860 - 1878, n.d.; 40102 (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - Vest and wallet belonging to Tilden, 40103; Oversized. (Box 99)
  - XI. C. Family papers, 1834 - 1929; 40104
    Although a few legal documents and items predating Tilden's birth are present, the vast majority of the series is made up of genealogical research assembled by Tilden, with further material added by Mrs. Emma Smith, the wife of his private secretary George W. Smith and final trustee of the Tilden estate. Also included is a folder of school work by his cousin, Julia Barnes, dating from 1834.
    - Genealogical research, 1898 - 1929, n.d.; 40105
      Largely collected by Mrs. George W. Smith
      - 1898 - 1929, 40106 (Box 87, Folder 3-4)
      - Undated, 40107 (Box 87, Folder 5-9)
      - Undated, 40108 (Box 88, Folder 1-5)
      - Undated, 40109 (Box 89, Folder 1-5)
      - Undated, 40110 (Box 90, Folder 1-2)
      - Undated, 40111; Oversized. (Box 91, Folder 7-8)
    - Legal documents, 40112 (Box 90, Folder 3-7)
    - School papers of Julia P. Barnes, ca. 1834; 40113 (Box 90, Folder 8)